A. Hildebrandt Papers
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress
A. Hildebrandt Papers 1826-1943 (bulk 1910-1930)
MSS25916
Hildebrandt, A. (Alfred), 1870-1949
9,000 items 98 containers plus 1 oversize 40 linear feet
Manuscript Division Library of Congress Washington, D.C.
German author on aeronautical subjects, pioneer in aviation, and the first European to support the experiments of the Wright Brothers, full name: Alfred Louis Heinrich Hildebrandt. Correspondence, notes, diaries, clippings, scrapbooks, pamphlets, periodicals, books, maps and charts, pictures and photographs, and other material collected by Hildebrandt on the history and development of aviation, with the focus on Germany, including personal papers relating to his career as a pioneer and advocate of aeronautics.
Selected Search Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the Library's online catalog. They are grouped by name of person or organization, by subject or location, and by occupation and listed alphabetically therein.
People
Albert, Prince of Schleswig-Holstein-Glücksburg--Correspondence.; Alexander, Patrick Young, 1867-1943--Correspondence.; Chanute, Octave, 1832-1910--Correspondence.; Damm, Ernst A.--Correspondence.; Feldhaus, Gilbert W.--Correspondence.; Grade, Hans, 1879-1946--Correspondence.; Hildebrandt, A. (Alfred), 1870-1949.; Ravenstein, Hans--Correspondence.; Scheimpflug, Karl--Correspondence.; Zeppelin, Ferdinand, Graf von, 1838-1917--Correspondence.
Subjects
Aeronautical sports.; Aeronautics, Commercial.; Aeronautics, Military.; Aeronautics--Germany.; Aeronautics--Law and legislation.; Aeronautics--Societies, etc.; Aeronautics.; Inventions.; Meteorology.
Occupations
Authors.; Aviators.
Administrative Information
Provenance
The papers of A. Hildebrandt, German writer on aeronautical subjects, pioneer in aviation, and the first European to support the experiments of Wilbur and Orville Wright, were received in two collections. The first was purchased for the Aeronautics Division of the Library of Congress in 1932; the second was received as a gift in 1947. The collection was transferred to the Manuscript Division from the Aeronautics Division in 1954.
Additional Guides
The Hildebrandt Papers were described at the time of the second acquisition in the Library of Congress Quarterly Journal of Current Acquisitions 4, no. 4 (August 1947): 25-26; and mentioned in the Quarterly Journal of Current Acquisitions 12, no. 3 (May 1955): 121.
Access and Restrictions
The papers of A. Hildebrandt are open to research. Researchers are advised to contact the Manuscript Reading Room prior to visiting. Many collections are stored off-site and advance notice is needed to retrieve these items for research use.
Biographical Note
Date Event
1870 Born, Wittingen, Kreis Isenhagen, Germany Educated: Kriegschule; Universität (Naturwissenschaftliche Fakultät); Technische Hochschule; Bergakademie; received doctor of philosophy degree
1893 First association with aeronautics Artillery officer
1898 Commander of airship detachment Teacher of aviation in Officer's Institute Member, editorial board of Moedebeck's Illustrierte Aeronautische Mitteilungen
circa 1902 Edited Die Königlich preussische Luftschiffer Abteilung Berlin
1907 Made trip to United States Member, Kriege International Kommission für wissenschaftlicne Luftschiffahrt President, International Kommission zur Herstellung von aeronitischen Landkarten Published Die Luftschiffahrt nach ihrer geschichtlichen und gegenwärtigen Entwicklung (tanslated into English and Spanish)
1908 Published Graf Ferdinand von Zeppelin
1909 Published Aviatik Published Die Brüder Wright; enine Studie über die Entwicklung der Flugmaschine von Lilienthal bis Wright
1910 President, International Kommission für Luftschifferkarten
1911 Published Flugwesen Published Vergleich der Temperatur suf dem Brocken und in der gleichen Höhe der freien Atmosphäre auf grundneuerer Ballon-und Drachenaufstiege
1914 Edited Die Arbeiten der "Rostocker Luftware" in Friedrichshöle bei Rostock im Jahre 1913
1918 Published Deutsches Flugwesen
1930 Joined National Socialist Party
1938 Dropped from membership in National Socialist Party
1949 Died in Germany
Scope and Content Note
The papers of Alfred Louis Heinrich Hildebrandt (1870-1949) extend from 1826 to 1943, with the bulk of the material concentrated in the period 1910-1930. A pioneer in aviation, Hildebrandt was a German author on aeronautical subjects and the first European to support the experiments of the Wright Brothers. His collection focuses on the history of aviation in Germany from the time of balloon experiments to the development of airplanes in World War II. Included is material on aviation sports, inventions, laws, meteorology, aviation societies, transportation, and other activities, both national and international, in addition to personal papers on his career and aeronautics. The papers consist of correspondence, notes, diaries, clippings, scrapbooks, pamphlets, periodicals, books, maps and charts, pictures and photographs, and indexes.
Correspondents include Albert, Prince of Schleswig-Holstein-Glücksburg, Patrick Young Alexander, Octave Chanute, Ernst A. Damm, Hans Grade, Hans Ravenstein, and Graf Ferdinand von Zeppelin.
Arrangement of the Papers
This collection is arranged alphabetically by subject or type of material.
http://lccn.loc.gov/mm81025916
Container List
- Accidents (Box 1)
  - Airplanes, accident at Schleiz
  - Airships
    - Dixmude (German)
    - Nobile, Umberto, tragedy of Italia (Italian airship) on an expedition to the North Pole
      - I) Until 30 June 1928
      - II) From 1 July 1928 until 1 Jan. 1929 (Box 2)
    - R 101 (British), its fall on 5 Oct. 1930 (as told in newspaper clippings)
  - Balloons
  - General (Box 3)
    - 1926 (organized first according to commercial, military and private; then according to country)
    - General observations; then according to country, 1927-1928
- Aerodynamics (Box 4)
  - Periodical articles
  - Reprints
  - Special articles
  - Work of special institutes
- Africa (including Hildebrandt's correspondence to Theobald von Bethmann-Hollweg) (Box 5)
- Airlines
  - Advertisements
  - Luft Hansa (Box 6)
  - Non-German
- Air mail (Box 7)
- Air raid protection
- Aircraft industry
  - Specific factories
    - BFW-Bavarian Airplane Works
    - BMW-Bavarian Motor Works
    - Dietrich-Gobiet Airplane Works
    - Dornier
    - Focke-Wulf
    - Gustav Otto Works
    - Hannover Wagon Works
    - Heinkel (Box 8)
    - Junkers I and II and Junkers private
    - Rhine Aero Works GMBH Dusseldorf-Ober Rassel (Box 9)
    - Rohrbach
    - Rumpler Works
    - Non-German
  - Catalogues of industries from A-H
  - Aeronautical Chamber of Commerce of America
  - Articles on the management of industry
  - General articles (Box 10)
  - Prager Press
- Airports (Box 11)
  - Specific airports
    - Berlin-Tempelhof
    - Essen-Mulheim
    - Hamburg
  - Observatories
    - Rostock
    - Urkinnden
  - Non-German (Box 12)
  - Clubs
    - Berlin-Johannisthal
    - Flug und Hafen
  - General
    - 1926
    - 1927-1928 (Box 13)
    - All years
- Airships (Box 14)
  - Specific
    - RK27 Airship
    - LZ 127
      - Important articles
      - Until Aug. 1928
      - From Sept. 1928 on
      - 1929
      - From 1930 on, important articles (Box 15)
      - ZR III
    - Zeppelins
      - 30 July 1924-30 Oct. 1924
      - 1 Nov. 1924-30 Dec. 1925
      - 3 Jan. 1927-1929 (Box 16)
      - Jan. 1930 on
      - General
  - Systems
    - Boernier system-ocean crossing airships
    - Description of the airship system LEPS
  - Zeppelin, Graf Ferdinand von
    - Zeppelin personally
    - Graf Zeppelin and his gains from air ship travel
  - Periodicals (Box 17)
    - Hildebrandt articles on Graf Ferdinand von Zeppelin
    - Moedebeck's Handbuch der Luftshiffahrt
    - Zeitschrift fur Luftschiffahrt
    - Zeppelin airships in Frankfurter Zeitung (Dr. Hugo Eckener)
    - Newspaper clippings
  - General
    - Airship or airplane
    - World airship travel
    - Zeppelin-Eckener charity (Box 18)
    - Pictures
    - Statistics
    - General
- America, 1923-1924
- Altitude flying (Box 19)
  - Specific
    - Rubber balloons
    - Research
  - General
    - Until 1928
    - 1929-1934
    - 1933-1935
    - Articles
- Aviators (Box 20)
  - Specific
    - Byrd, Richard E.
    - Chamberlain, Clarence
    - Euler, August, and Hans Grade
    - Fieseler, Gerhard, and Marcel Doret duel on 23 Oct. 1927
    - Köhl, Hermann, ocean flight (Box 21)
    - Könnecke, Otto, ocean Asia flight
    - Lilienthal, Ottto
    - Lindbergh, Charles
    - Mittelholzer, Walter-Gouzy, Rene, Africa flight, 1926 (Box 22)
    - Nungesser, Charles Eugène Jules Marie, and Francois Coli
    - De Pinedo, Francesco
    - Dumont, Santos
  - General
    - Air captains
    - Officers and engineers
    - Personal histories
    - Prewar pilots
    - Pictures
    - General
- Awards (Box 23)
- Balloons
  - Air currents on balloons
  - History including particular flights
  - Materials
  - Meteorological
  - Military
  - Passengers: de'Argenson and Montgolfier
  - Periodicals: Der Freiballoon
- Races (Box 24)
  - Gordon Bennett Cup
    - 1908
    - 1907-1912
    - 1927
    - General
  - Types (Box 25)
    - Barrage balloons
    - Fixed balloons
    - Free balloons
    - Hot air balloons
      - Berlin's
      - Brunner's
      - Marek-Emma system
      - Hildebrandt's articles on hot air balloons (Box 26)
      - Newspaper clippings and periodicals
  - Postcards (mostly comic)
- Bibliography (Box 27)
  - Book reviews
  - General
- Budges
- Charity, Luftfahrerspende
- Control, automatic
- Design (Box 28)
  - Specific
    - Avia
    - BMW
    - Boerner
    - Budig airplane
    - Dornier
    - Focke-Wulf
    - Junkers
  - Airplane spotting
  - Altitude planes
  - Czechoslovakian military planes
  - Non-German
  - Sport planes (Box 29)
  - General
    - Blueprints
    - Pictures
    - General
  - Education and propaganda
- Engines (Box 30)
  - Airplane
    - Specific
      - Airship and balloon engines
      - BMW airplane engines
      - German airplane engines
      - Non-German airplane engines
    - Periodicals
      - Illustrierte Motor Zeitung
      - Luftfahrt Rundschau, periodical for aviation technique and airship flight, 1930
      - Technical part of the reports for air travel, 1921
    - Accessories and parts
    - Propellers
  - Non-airplane
- Exhibitions (Box 31)
  - Specific
    - Aero-Salon, Paris, France
      - 1926
      - 1930
    - Airships, Dusseldorf, 1925-1926
    - Exhibitions for charity, Dusseldorf, 1926
    - ILA (Internationale Luft-und Raumfahrtausstellung), Berlin, 1928
    - Ghent, Belgium, 1913 (Box 32)
    - Oldenburg, 1927
    - Prague, Czechoslovakia, 1927
  - General
  - Dec. 1911-Nov. 1913
  - 1924
  - Undated
- Explorations (Box 33)
- Flight of animals
- Fuel
- Gliders
  - Ursinus
  - Good articles on gliding
  - General
- Goering, Hermann
- Hangars (Box 34)
- History
  - Specific
    - Balloons
    - Gliders
  - General
    - Early French periodicals
    - General history of aviation in America (Wright's Scientific American, 1890, etc.)
    - General history of aviation in Germany
    - History of flying from Icarus to 1904
    - History of flying from the Middle Ages to 1910 (Box 35)
    - History of flying (alphabetical from M to Z)
    - Newspapers of the nineteenth century, American and English
    - Humor and poetry
      - About locks and keys
      - Folk songs about Zeppelins
      - Humor and caricatures
      - Nonsense in German newspapers
      - Rotschenrenther, About Winged Wheels and Eagle Wings
      - General
- Indexes (Box 36)
- Instruments
  - Specific
    - Compass
    - Lights
    - Radio
    - Sound waves
    - General radio
  - General
    - Measuring instruments
    - General
- Insurance (Box 37)
  - Specific
    - Balloons in Denmark
    - Kasko case
    - Nopitsch, Heinrich, in Würzburg
  - General
    - Accident damage
    - Iduna Zeitung
- International relations
  - Commissions
    - Comité juridique international de l'aviation
    - International Commission for Scientific Airship Travel (2 pieces)
    - International Commission's Observations, 1903 (4 vols.)
    - Permanent International Commission for Aviation (Box 38)
  - Congresses
    - First International Congress for Aerial Security
    - International Aeronautical Federation Conference in Zurich, Switzerland, 1911
    - International Commission for Aerial Navigation
  - General
    - Freedom of the air
    - Scientific
    - General articles
    - General conferences
- Inventions and patents (Box 39)
  - French
  - German
    - Patentschrifte
    - General
    - Kites
    - Laws
  - Government
    - Air Board, 1926
    - Air mail traffic
    - Air Ministry (budget 1928)
    - Air Ministry (general I and II)
    - Bulletin for the Prussian Administration of the Interior (Box 40)
    - Reichstag meetings
    - Secretary of state for air, Erhard Milch
    - Swiss Confederation's Air Board
  - Law
    - Case of Arthur Miller, accused of corruption
    - German lawyers' paper
    - Reich's Bulletin of Laws
  - General
    - By state
    - General I and II (Box 41)
- Literature
- Locomotives
- Maps and charts (Box 42)
  - Russia
  - Strassburg and environs
  - Illustrations
    - Chart paper
    - Photogrammetry
    - Route of the sea planes, 1926 (Box 43)
  - Writings
    - Articles about maps
    - Cartographic clubs
    - Correspondence about maps
    - Dr. Peuker
    - Zeppelin, Grad Ferdinand von, urges the importance of maps, and miscellany
- Materials (Box 44)
- Medicine
  - Dreams and flying
  - General
- Meteorology
  - Specific
    - Lindenburg
      - Observatory
      - Temperature over Lindenburg (chart)
      - German Flying Weather Service (I and II) (Box 45)
      - Royal Russian Academy of Scientists
    - Articles
      - Radiation in the stratosphere I and II
      - Sky (Box 46)
      - Troposphere and stratosphere
    - Periodicals
      - Annals of Hydrography and Maritime Meteorological
      - German Meteorological Yearbook
      - Meteorologishe Zeitschrift
      - Das Wetter
    - General
      - Non-German articles
      - Scientific German articles (Box 47)
      - General
- Military (Box 48)
  - Specific
    - Air force
    - Prussian airship troops
    - Zeppelin airships in the war
  - Periodicals
    - Krieger Zeitung
    - Memories of the war, 1914
    - Military magazines, general
  - General
    - History
    - Non-German articles
    - Various things about the war (1914-1918) collected by Hildebrandt (Box 49)
    - General I and II
- Models
- Navigation
- Newspapers (Box 50)
  - Specific
    - Dingler's Polytechnisches journal, 1826-1859
    - Dusseldorfer Stadtanzeiger
    - Frankfurter Zeitung
    - Kölnische Zeitung
      - 1923
      - 1924
      - 1930 (Box 51)
      - 1931
    - Königsberger Hartungsche Zeitung, 1925
    - La Plata (Argentina)
      - Aug.-Sept. 1924
      - 1 Jan.-24 Mar. 1925
    - Preussische Zeitung (Box 52)
    - Volkischer Beobachter, 1933-1936
  - Collections of clippings from various newspapers
    - 1908-1909
    - 1928-1929
    - General
    - 1907 (Box 53)
- Personal (Box 54)
  - Hildebrandt's writings
    - Articles
      - Airship Flight
      - Aviation (1908-1909)
      - Luftfahrt Rundschau, 1911-1912
      - Weser Zeitung
  - Articles in newspapers by and about Hildebrandt (Box 55)
    - 1885-1907
    - 1908-1910
    - 1911-1934 (Box 56)
    - 1935-1937
  - Articles by Hildebrandt (Box 57)
  - Articles by and about Hildebrandt in the newspapers, 1938-1939 (Box 58)
  - Lectures
    - 1911
    - Celebration speech
    - Club
    - General (including Officers Institute lecture on balloons) and advertisements
  - Correspondence
    - Business, Albatross Works
    - Deutscher Luftfahrt Verband
      - Confidential
      - Until Oct. 1910 (Box 59)
      - 1910-1911
      - 1911
      - 1912
      - 1922
      - 1925
    - Ring freier Luftfahrtsachverstandiger (Circle of free aviation experts) (Box 60)
    - Societies, regarding lectures Hildebrandt should give
    - Government
      - Air Traffic Ministry
      - Legal advisor for aviation
      - Nationalsozialistische Deutsche Arbeiterpartei
    - Periodicals and publishers
      - Brockhaus
      - Exchange "Luftflette" for foreign magazines Kölnische Zeitung
        - General, 1928-1929
        - Rossman
      - Königersberger Allgemeine Zeitung (Box 61)
      - Lokal Anzeiger
      - Sonntag Morgen-Stuart
      - Publishers I and II
    - General
      - Boerner, Arno
      - Frauds
      - International Aeronautical Federation, 1911-1914
      - Lufthansa
      - St. Andreasberger's Flying Week
      - World exhibition in Ghent, Belgium, 1913 (Box 62)
    - Personal
      - 1910-1911
      - 1920-1925 See Container 63, 1925-1928
      - 1927-1928
      - Alexander, Patrick Young
      - Americans: U.S. War Department, aviation clubs, etc., 1900-1915
      - Chanute, Octave, including letter of introduction to Wilbur Wright for Hildebrandt
      - Charities
      - Damm, Ernst A., 1927
      - 1920-1928 (Box 63)
      - Feldhaus, Gilbert;, Sauer, Otto; etc. (Box 64)
      - Ravenstein, Hans
      - Royalty (Albert, Prince of Schleswig-Holstein-Gluckernurg)
      - Scheimpflug, Karl
      - Siegert, Wilhelm
      - Zeppelin, Grad Ferdinand von, photostats of letters to Hildebrandt
      - Miscellaneous I-II
      - Miscellaneous III-V (Box 65)
  - Miscellany (Box 66)
    - America, album with mementos and correspondence, including with Octave Chanute, 1906-1909
    - Autobiography of early life
    - Hildebrandt's World War I diary, photographs and souvenir
    - Flag dropped from Zeppelin
    - Flyers Reserve Division 4 (pictures)
    - Jubilee (fifty years) for Hildebrandt as an aviator, 12 May 1943
    - Lists of flyers (Box 67)
- Locks, keys, and coats of arms
  - Locks and Keys and the Locksmith's Trade by Hildebrandt and Ernst A. Damm
    - Manuscripts I-III
  - Linguistic studies
    - Of the words: locks, etc.
    - Of the words: chamberlain (Box 68)
  - History
    - Ancient history
    - Burglary in the times of the old Greeks and Romans
  - Bibliography
  - Material for citing for an article about locks
  - Pictures
  - Coats of arms
  - Explanations and pictures
  - Stereotype plates I-V
  - Stereotype plates I-V
- Personal (Box 69)
  - Luftflotte, 1910-1911, under editorship of Hildebrandt
  - Possessions and photographs
  - Postcard album
  - Review of Hildebrandt's book Vom Flugahnen to Altitude Flying (From Presentiments of flight to Altitude Flying)
  - Roeloff, W. M., speech
  - Pictures, general
- Photography (Box 70)
- Records
- Religion and superstitions
  - Patron saints
  - Superstitions
- Rotor planes
  - Manuscript on Flettner-Rotor planes
  - General
- Safety equipment, parachutes
- Schools (Box 71)
  - Problems of education and schools
  - Types of schools
- Societies
  - Specific
    - Aero clubs
    - Les aeronautes (Box 72)
    - Akademische Fliegerschaft
    - Berliner Verein fűr Luftshiffahrt (Box 73)
    - Bundes Deutscher Flieger
    - Deutscher Luftfaht Verband
      - I, Part 1
      - I, Part 2-II (Box 74)
    - Deutscher Verein zur Forderung der Luftschiffahrt (Box 75)
    - Lilienthal Gesellschaft
    - Oberheinischer Verin fűr Luftshiffahrt
    - Rheinische-Westfalische Fluggellschaft
    - Vereins einemaliger Kameraden der Luftschiffer Truppen
    - Vereins Flugmachine
    - Wissenschaftliche Gesellschaft fűr Luftfahrt I
    - Wissenschaftliche Gesellschaft fűr Luftfahrt II (Box 76)
  - Types
    - British clubs except Aero Club
    - Italian clubs
    - French
    - German club, scientific
    - German clubs, general (Box 77)
    - General I and II, including Luftschiffbau Zeppelin Gesellschaft
- Speed
  - Speed and range
  - General (Box 78)
- Sport
  - Races
    - Germany
      - Gliding
        - Coastal gliding competitions
          - 1923
          - 1923-1925
          - 1924
          - 1927 (Rossitten)
        - Rhon Gliding Competition
          - 1924
          - 1925
          - 1926
          - 1927 (Box 79)
          - 1928
          - 1930
          - 1931
        - St. Andreasberger Gliding Competition
      - Powered flying
        - Airman's Day
          - 1925 (June 11-16)
          - 1926
          - 1927
          - 1928
        - Berlin Flying Week, 1909
        - D.L.V. Reliability Flight (Box 80)
        - Flying Day at Goslar, 1927
        - Flying days
          - 1926
          - 1927-1928
        - German round-trip flight, 1925
        - German Seaflight Competition, 1926 (I and II) (Box 81)
        - Rhine Flying Competition (I and II)
        - Rhineland Liberation Flight, 1930, and D.L.V.
        - Reliability flight
        - Saxon flight, 1927
        - South German flight, 1926 (Box 82)
    - Italy
      - Coppa d'Italia
      - La Gazetta dello Sport
    - International
      - Air meet, Zurich, Switzerland, 1927
      - European Return Trip Race, 1929
        - List of participating airplanes and candidates
        - Newspaper write-ups (Box 83)
      - International Flying Competition in Munich, Sept. 1925
    - Schneider Trophy
      - 1927
      - 1929-1931
    - General races
      - Races, 1912
      - 1924 (world circling)
      - 1925 (Box 84)
      - 1928-1930
    - Competition notices
    - Periodicals about sports
      - Flugsport sea flight competitions
      - Der Sportflieger, 1926-1929
      - General articles, newspaper write-ups (Box 85)
    - General articles (Box 86)
      - German air sports, 1930
      - Sport and the German Air Ministry, 1927
      - Youth and flying for sport
    - Convocations of various flying celebrations
    - Sport Press Club
    - General
- Terminology (Box 87)
  - Airplane names
  - Luftwaffe technical dictionary
  - General
- Test flights
- Transportation (Box 88)
  - Management
    - Freight
    - Timetables (I and II) (Box 89)
    - Special flights (Box 90)
      - Flights over the ocean in Junkers, 1927
      - Flights, 1914, peaceful
      - Flights, particular (Box 91)
  - Articles
    - Air, the ideal medium for travel
    - Dusseldorf's place in air traffic
    - Transportation in Krefeld
    - French articles
    - General German articles
  - Periodicals
    - Air travel until 1928 described in newspaper clippings
    - Transportation, non-German, 1927-1928, clippings
    - General periodicals (Box 92)
    - Ulderup's (very confidential) lecture about air travel, 1929
- Miscellaneous (Box 93-96)
- Hildebrandt's index to collection (Box 97)
  - A-M
  - N-Z and supplementary file (Box 98)
- Oversize certificates and diplomas (Box OV 99)